A Guide to the Papers of the Quinby Family 1759(1800-1898)1968
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Quinby Family 1759(1800-1898)1968
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2338, -a, -b, 2871
This collection consists of ca. 1300 items (7 Hollinger boxes and one oversize folder, 2.8 linear shelf feet).
H. W. Symonds
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library in four groups:
Collection #2338 was given to the Library by Mrs. Charles, G. Evans of Danville, Virginia, and Mrs. Margaret Upshur Franklin of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, on June 24, 1946.
Collection #2338-a was given to the Library by Upshur Evans of Cleveland, Ohio, on October 30, 1953.
Collection #2338-b was given to the Library by Upshur Evans of Cleveland, Ohio, on January 31, 1969.
Collection # 2871 was given to the Library by Mrs. Charles G. Evans of Chatham, Virginia, on February 5, 1948.
Scope and Content Information
The Quinby Family Papers consists of ca. 1300 items (7 Hollinger boxes and one oversize folder, 2.8 linear shelf feet, 1759(1800-1898)1968, papers of the Upshur, Teackle, Quinby, and other related families of the Eastern Shores of Maryland and Virginia, specifically Somerset County, Maryland, and Accomack and Northampton counties, Virginia. The collection includes correspondence, legal and finanical papers, a letterbook, ledgers and journals, class notebooks, commonplace books, genealogical information, prayerbooks, and memorandum books. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence of Elizabeth (Upshur) Teackle, Littleton Dennis Teackle, Elizabeth Anne Upshur (Teackle) Quinby, Aaron Balderston Quinby, and Upshur Balderston Quinby with friends, family, and business associates.
Much of the early correspondence, 1778 to 1799, is with Andrew D. Campbell. Campbell and his wife were British friends of the Teackles and Upshurs and he continued to write lengthy letters to members of these families until his death in 1853.
In 1800, Elizabeth Upshur (1783-1837) married Littleton Dennis Teackle (1777-1850) of Princess Anne, Somerset County, Maryland. Many of her letters from the period 1800-1837 were written to: her, husband; her daughter, Elizabeth Anne Upshur Teackle (1801-1875); and her sister, Anne Eyre of Northampton County, Virginia. These letters are of a personal nature but contain a few references to historical events, such as one of the British landings in the Chesapeake Bay area (Havre de Grace) in May 1813. One letter, dated December 2, 1778, from Nancy Cunningham (signed "Ruralinda") to Sally Teackle, has a note attached, written by Elizabeth Upshur Teackle on October 1, 1829, which provides background on the 1778 letter. The letter refers to Nancy Cunningham's flight from Philadelphia in the Fall of 1777 or 1778 and to her later return and describes the whereabouts of Severn Teackle, who was being held as a prisoner of war by the British on Long Island in New York.
Littleton Dennis Teackle owned and managed a ship supply company in Princess Anne, Somerset County, Maryland, from 1805 to 1807. A letterbook from that business contains a great deal of historical information relating to the period prior to the War of 1812. It describes Teackle's business and lists materials he supplied, such as wooden structural components for ships, makes references to domestic and foreign affairs, and contains many other details relating to his daily business operations during this period.
Apparently Mr. Teackle was away from home much of the time between 1807 and 1815 and between 1824 and 1836. During the earlier period he may have been involved in a shipping business with headquarters in Baltimore; he was a member of the Maryland House of Delgates during the later period.
Included in Teackle's unbound correspondence is a letter from Henry Clay written in 1825 regarding paper money and another from James Madison on primary schools in Maryland written in 1826, in which he states some of his views on education. In 1836 Teackle wrote to Thomas R. Joynes of Accomack County, Virginia, as a member of the Maryland House of Delegates, regarding that body's consideration of a plan to build a railroad through the Eastern Shore of Maryland. He presented this information in order that Mr. Joynes could, if he were agreeable, support the continuance of the road south to Norfolk, Virginia. A railroad was not actually built through this area until more than forty-five years later.
Most of the material dated 1838-1853 consists of personal, business and legal business papers of Elizabeth Anne Upshur (Teackle) Quinby and her husband, Aaron Balderston Quinby (1795-1853), a Baltimore lawyer whom she married in 1839. Major correspondents include Henry Clay, dated 1842 on the Whig Party; Quinby's brother, Jesse B. Quinby, including on English investment in the U. S.; and the Reverend J. W. Hoffman, a minister in Monroe, Connecticut, and a friend of the family. Material from this period includes several letters from United States representative Issac D. Jones and others to Secretary of State Daniel Webster, recommending Aaron B. Quinby for an appointment in the United States Patent Office, and correspondence of Quinby with representatives of the U.S. Navy, including James K. Paulding, George E. Badger and James Biddle, whom he was asking to test and adopt his invention to prevent steam boiler explosions. Also included is an 1841 letter to Charles Stewart regarding ship propeller.
Between 1854 and 1875, Elizabeth A. U. Quinby corresponded with relatives and friends, such as Henrietta Chauncey, C.E. Le Cato and a Mrs. C. Williams.
Aaron B. Quinby's legal papers include a copy of his will, powers of attorney to collect property for clients, and his claim to property in the possessions of his wife's father. One power of attorney concerns lands in the Virginia Military District in the State of Ohio which were acquired as an award for service rendered by a soldier during the Revolution.
Much of the personal correspondence between 1860 and 1897 is that of Upshur Balderston Quinby (1841-1898), son of Mrs. Elizabeth A. U. and Aaron B. Quinby. Upshur Quinby attended the University of Virginia (1860-1861), and later became a highly respected lawyer in Onancock, Virginia. He and Georgeanna ("Georgie") Richardson (1845-1896) were married in 1864 and had seven children.
Upshur Quinby's early correspondence with his mother includes references to his life as a student at the University of Virginia, such as a description of a hike to "Monticello," and records rumored and actual events at the beginning of the Civil War. In 1879 Mr. Quinby was involved with the Onancock Academy in Onancock, Accomack County, Virginia. Related correspondence includes letters from applicants for teaching positions and recommendations in support of several of them from Professor John B. Minor of the University of Virginia.
Quinby was a candidate for judge of the Eastern Shore Circuit in 1880 and his correspondence for that year includes letters of support from friends and associates including: Charles U. Williams; G. W. Le Cato; L. R. Warren; Robert Thruston Hubard; Judge John M. Jeffries; John B. Minor; Richard Lee Tuberville Beale of the U. S. House of Representatives; and W. W. Walker. Several of these promised to recommend him to the governor of Virginia, Frederick W. M. Holliday.
Quinby's personal correspondence from 1883 to 1897 consists chiefly of letters from relatives and friends, such as Adaline M. Swarts, Dr. W. F. Quinby, I. W. Quinby, and L. D. Teackle Quinby, and includes many letters concerned with genealogy. In 1896 Quinby received many letters of condolence on Mrs. Quinby's death.
Most of Upshur B. Quinby's legal and financial papers, which date fron 1828 to 1894, pertain to properties which he and Mrs. Quinby owned in Accomack County, Virginia. The papers include deeds, copies of deeds, land records, and receipts for purchases of building materials. Included in this section is some of the Quinby's professional correspondence relating to general legal claims and debt collection.
The genealogical material in this collection includes information regarding the related Andrews, Balderston, Scarburgh, Stockley, Sturges, Teackle, Upshur, Walter, and West families, dating back to the 16th century. Much of the correspondence dating from 1886 to 1931 contains family information, probably in response to inquiries from Upshur Quinby. The genealogy section of the collection contains the baptismal certificate of Upshur B. Quinby, birth and death records from a family bible, notes, charts, and newspaper clippings. Other genealogical information appears in a psalter and a Book of Common Prayer which also contains slave records, the three commonplace books, and the oversize material.
The bound volumes include two commonplace books of poems written by Elizabeth U. Teackle and her daughter and thirteen record books kept by Upshur B. Quinby. The latter include three University of Virginia class notebooks; four memoranda book which are almost indecipherable; two account books containing records of fees paid to the Onancock Academy; and three books containing financial accounts of Quinby's farm and legal practice.
Organization
This collection has been divided into six series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal and Financial Papers, III. Genealogy, IV. Miscellaneous Papers, V. Bound Volumes, and VI. Oversize Material.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1778-1817, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1818 Apr-1857, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1858-1911, 1927, 1931, n.d., 7 folders (Box 3)
- Financial and Legal Papers
  - Legal Papers of Upshur B. Quinby 1882-1894, n.d., 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Legal Papers of Upshur B. Quinby 1878-1884, 1893-1894 (Box 4)
    re Debt Collections
  - Financial Papers: Accounts of Upshur B. Quinby 1882-1891, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Legal Papers of Aaron B. Quinby 1840, n.d. (Box 4)
    includes Business Correspondence
  - Legal Papers of Aaron B. Quinby 1834-1841, n.d. (Box 4)
    re Captain William White
  - Legal Papers of Aaron B. Quinby 1837-1842 (Box 4)
    re Invention of Steam Boiler Safety Device
  - Legal Papers 1843, 1885 (Box 4)
    re Will of Aaron B. Quinby
  - Miscellaneous Financial and Legal Papers 1880, 1888, n.d. (Box 4)
- Genealogy
  - Family Records and Annotated pages Removed from Bible ca. 1794 and ca. 1850 (Box 5)
  - Baptismal Certificate of Upshur Balderston Quinby 1844 (Box 5)
  - Charts and Lists 1885-1892, n.d. (Box 5)
    re Upshur, Teackle, Quinby, Stockley, Cutler, Revell and Scarburgh Families
  - Newspaper Clippings 1891 (Box 5)
    re Quinby Family
  - "My Birthplace and My Home" by Edna Evans Bell 1968, TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Papers
  - Copy Book of Upshur B. Quinby ca. 1850 [?] (Box 5)
  - Notes n.d. (Box 5)
    re Anatomy
  - Poems 1862, 1891, n..d. (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1844-1895 (Box 5)
- Bound Volumes
  - Psalter 1759 (Box 5)
    Genealogy
  - Book of Common Prayer 1768 (Box 5)
  - Letterbook 1805-1807 (Box 5)
    Business records of Littleton Dennis Teackle
  - Commonplace Book 1808-1862 (Box 6)
    Poems and notes of Elizabeth U. Teackle
  - Commonplace Book 1826-1872 (Box 6)
    Poems and notes of Elizabeth A. U. Teackle Quinby and genealogical notes
  - Class notebook kept by Upshur B. Quinby while a student at the University of Virginia 1860-1961 (Box 6)
    in a law class taught by John B. Minor
  - Legal notebook kept by Upshur B. Quinby while a student at the University of Virginia 1860-1861, 1870-1898 (Box 6)
    includes business records from a later date
  - Class notebook kept by Upshur B. Quinby while a student at the University of Virginia 1860-1861, 1871-1876 (Box 6)
    in a law class taught by John B. Minor; includes business records from a later date.
  - Class notebook kept by Upshur B. Quinby while a student at the University of Virginia 1860-1861, 1878-1882 (Box 6)
    in a class taught by James P. Holcombe; includes business records from a later date
  - Memorandum Book 1876-1877 (Box 7)
  - Journal of The Onancock Academy 1877-1890 (Box 7)
  - Ledger of Tuition Fees from The Onancock Academy 1877-1885 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum Book 1878-1879 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum Book 1880-1881 (Box 7)
  - Ledger 1881-1896 (Box 7)
    Farm business records of Upshur B. Quinby
  - Memorandum Book 1882-1883 (Box 7)
  - Commonplace Book 1887 (Box 7)
  - Ledger 1896-1897 (Box 7)
  - Ledger 1901-1902 (Box 7)
    Law fees
  - Commonplace Book n.d. (Box 7)
  - Papers removed from volumes number 12, 15, and 18 1877-1897 (Box 7)
- Oversize Material
  - Poems of Elizabeth Upshur Teackle 1831
  - Certificate of Residence in Accomack County, Virginia, of Upshur B. Quinby 1862 Sep 30
  - License of Upshur B. Quinby to practice as attorney in the Courts of the Commonwealth of Virginia 1864 Jan 20, handwritten
  - Same as above on vellum 1864 Jan 20
  - Deed, Edward K. Snead, Executor of the Will of John Snead, deceased, to Thomas S. Richardson 1867 May 1
  - Family tree of the Quinby family (1690-18410 1879 May 11
  - Family tree of the Quinby family prepared by Thomas B. Quinby 1891 June 25
  - Application for membership in the National Society, Daughters of the American Colonists of Mrs. Elise Quinby Bell 1927
  - Family record of the Dennis and Teackle families from 1728 to 1811 n.d.
  - Table of descents of Edward Fisher, grandfather of Mrs. Elizabeth Fisher Seymour (deceased, 1864 Jun) n.d.